[Applause]
[Music]
Welcome back to the channel!
This week we're going to try to
close the loop on
quantum processors. If you remember,
we did a first episode
explaining why they were interesting,
what advantages they would bring us, and
giving a first glimpse of how they
work. Since it's complicated to understand
how they work, we've done several
episodes trying to explain the
different concepts of quantum mechanics
that support how they function.
Today, what I'm going to try to do is
somehow tie up all these loose ends
with a single theory:
string theory. String theory, in
a way, is what will try to
tie up all the loose ends we have,
unifying what's happening into a single theory.
For me, it's by far
the most elegant theory
that physics has ever created, for one simple
reason: it's simple. Within
the enormous complexity it entails,
within the complexity of all the
topics it deals with, it ultimately reduces it to a
fairly
simple theory. Let me make a very
quick aside. It's a response to...  A
comment I received a couple of months ago,
something like that, on the video about
virtual universes, Carlos Moreno was saying that, "
Hey, the way
these topics are being approached, all about
quantum physics and everything else, we're
seeing that, for example, there are already
things that work but haven't been
proven yet, this is starting to look like
religion, not philosophy, religion, however we
want to call it." And I
completely agree with him. It's
true that we're taking certain
leaps of faith, that we're having a certain
blind faith in physics,
mathematics, and science, let's say, around this.
More than anything because, until now, it has
never failed us. I mean, we've always
seen that in the end, the
simplest logic seems to work, and we've
always followed it. That's why I'm going to
explain string theory today.
Because for me, the most
important thing in physics,
mathematics, and science is
simplicity. Let's say I have something like this,
something I call the theory
of simplicity: simple,
elegant solutions are usually the
true ones, the ones behind it all.
And for example, this
string theory, it seems to me, is...  That
line, in any case, at the end of the
video I'm going to give you a couple
more examples to explain what I mean by this
simplicity theory.
Carlos, thank you very much for the comment
because we were there discussing it and it was really
entertaining. For this string theory, I
think the most important thing is that we go
step by step, and that's when we're going to
understand it well. Okay, it's taken me
several weeks to really get it
into my head and come up with a script
to try to explain it. It's not really
easy, but I think if we go
slowly, it's quite understandable. The
first thing is, where does this string theory come from?
Why does someone start
thinking about it? And before knowing what it
is, before that... well, the problem we
have is that if we look at
our universe, at known science, at
physics, at the mathematics that we already
have validated, what we see is that there are
four forces that remain
constant in the universe. Okay, that is to say,
almost everything in the universe is variable; that is to
say, there are a lot of things that,
depending on where you are, are one
thing or another, but there are four things that
always remain, and they are four
forces that we could consider something like
four laws that...
These four forces—
the electromagnetic force, the
weak nuclear force, the strong nuclear force, and
the force of gravity—are true throughout the universe. Logically,
if there are only four
important laws in the universe, someone might ask, "
What do they have in common?" or "What
common pattern could these four
laws have?" Well, the thing is, when they
started studying the laws, they realized that
three of them—the
electromagnetic force and the two nuclear forces—
could be simplified and
reduced to
simpler things, and said to be
practically the same but with small
deviations. However, the
force of gravity, every time they
tried to study it, every time they tried to reduce it
to what already existed, it was absolutely
impossible; it always failed. It's much
smaller than the other three, and it
behaves in a rather different way. This has
intrigued
physicists for centuries because there was no way to
equate it with the rest of what
we have in the universe. So, from
here, five string theories emerged. Okay, we
haven't explained what they're about yet,
but five theories emerged that try to
explain this.  This phenomenon, that is, they try to
reduce the four forces to something common
with small
variations. What these theories say
is that everything is actually composed
of tiny strings of energy, very, very
small.
If we go to the traditional model
of the electron, as you can see here,
we always thought that what we
had was matter—not
ourselves—that was composed of
the first small part that I distinguished. These were
molecules. These
molecules were nothing more than a collection of
atoms. Each of the atoms, in
reality, contained a
nucleus with protons and
neutrons, and
electrons, let's say, orbiting around in some way.
And if we took each of these
particles, what we actually had
inside were quarks, which,
in our mental representation, were
like little balls that orbited around and
interacted in
some way. And depending on what kind
of balls we had, we had
the different elements. The same thing
happened with light. We knew that light
was composed of photons, and
for us, photons were nothing more than a
kind of...  Not that it was capable of
moving through space and that it was what
we see, right? Well, what
String Theory tells you is that
everything is actually the same, okay? That
light, as well as—not electrons,
but the parts that make up electrons,
neutrons, and so on—all of
them are nothing more than strings, and
what differentiates them from each other is the way they
vibrate, okay? That is,
imagine we have a string and that we
have the ends vibrating up
and down, well, that would be, for
example, an electron, right? That we have one
end stationary and the other rotating? Well,
that would be a proton, to
give an example. Okay, so the
idea would be that everything is composed of the
same thing, which is a kind of string
of energy that, depending on how it
is moving, is a
subatomic particle of one type or another.
That is, from a quark to a photon,
right? The problem comes when you look at
the number of subatomic particles
discovered by humans, and you realize that you
say, "Hey, uh, if
depending on the..."  The way the
string vibrates... I have a particle. Well, I'm going
to need... Well, I don't know... I don't know how many
modes of vibration... and the problem is
that with the four dimensions
we're working with, that is, height, width,
and depth over
time, those four dimensions are
n't enough to have all the
modes of vibration that
string theory suggests. So, what I know is how it's
justified, to put it a
certain way, by adding
dimensions, okay? That is, dimensions
that we can't see, that we ca
n't interact with, but
that are there and that do allow for the
existence of those different modes of
vibration that we can
interact with. In fact, it's estimated that there should be
nine
normal dimensions plus time, that is, 10
dimensions in total. Interestingly,
this conclusion has also been reached
through other means, not only
through string theory but also
through methods of logical reasoning
and so on. It also arrives that there must always be
10 dimensions, which
makes this sound good, right?
But how is this explained? Because this
is very well said, very well said... you
end up...  To invent six
dimensions all at once and be so smug about it?
Because that's what you must be
thinking right now. It's not good. The
truth is, what the
theory says is that it's not quite like that.
What happens is that these six
additional dimensions are only
observable when we go to certain
sizes, to certain
subatomic measurements. How could we give an
example of this? If we imagine our
entire universe, if we
consider the entire universe to be the
equivalent, for example, of a pixel on the
screen of a higher universe, like
in the movie Mening Black, at the
end when the camera zooms out,
and it turns out that the entire universe is nothing
more than a child's marble. Well,
imagine that our entire universe is
a pixel, and that depending on what
moment in the universe we are in, it's on
or off for that
universe in which the pixel is located.
There we would have only one dimension, that is, there we would
be a point, a point
with only two values.
However, the moment we get closer
and closer and closer,
we see that here there are
four easily
locatable dimensions, that is, we have a
three-dimensional space.  Dimensional. And we have time, right? Well, let's
say that in some way,
mathematics and physics demonstrate that this would
also happen within
particles, that is, at the
subatomic level. We would also have these
additional dimensions. Let's say
this is a bit of a drawback of the theory,
but let's say it's also quite well
justified, at least
mathematically and physically. Although it might
seem that intuitively it isn't so much,
if you look at what I've explained
so far. For me, it has a
fundamental drawback, and that is that if we stick
with the theory, as far as we've gotten, there's
a problem, and that is that it doesn't have any
logic. And it doesn't have any logic
because what does it make sense for a
subatomic particle to have the shape of a string? I mean, something, even if it isn't,
but something like a sphere makes
much more sense, because it's a
much more perfect figure, it's
like something finished or
closed, while a string... well, it doesn't even
seem to make
sense. To say that there are strings
flying through the air... what the
theory says is that they aren't...
Strings that are
happily flying through space, and that's what
makes up matter. What they're
telling you is that these strings
are actually the junctions of things that
physicists have called by a
horrible name: branes. Okay, I'll
leave the name here because I've never
heard of it before, and I don't think I'll ever hear it again. Okay,
branes? What are these branes? Well, let's say
the universe can have a
certain number of properties. It can
have electromagnetic properties, it can have
nuclear properties, it can have, let's
say, certain characteristics. Okay,
let's stick with something as simple
as that. And let's say these are
characteristics that exist throughout the entire
universe at the same time. Imagine a balloon,
and I put several gases in it, like
oxygen, nitrogen, argon, whatever I want. A
bunch. Well, let's say it would be the
same situation. The gases
expand, they mix with each other, and
we have gases everywhere inside
the balloon. Well, in the universe it would be the
same. Let's say we would have a bunch
of properties all mixed together throughout
the universe, not with each other, and these strings...
These are actually
tiny connections between different
branes, such that we could say
each brane has a
kind of oscillation or movement, or
something like that, different from the others.
Imagine, there's a brane that moves
vertically and another brane that
moves horizontally. The result
would be a string that joins the two branes at a point. We're
talking about something very, very
small, a tiny amount of energy,
and with the different movements, it
achieves a specific vibration. If I
have a brane that, for example, moves in a
circular motion with another that also moves in a
circular motion, the vibration of that
string would be different from the previous one, and
that would give us a different subatomic particle. So,
with a certain
number of what are called "bananas,"
that is, properties that the
universe has, the connections between these
properties are what would form the
different types of strings, and the
different types of strings are what we
've said would be the different
subatomic particles. This is
really the key to the theory, and it's the
key to what I'm going to tell you
next. This theory solves two
fundamental problems. The first is when
we talk about gravity.  What we
explained at the beginning of the chapter, we did
n't see, is that the problem we
had with gravity is that it was
practically different from the other three
forces, despite being, let's say, a
fundamental force in the universe.
Well, the interesting thing is that what
the theory tells you is that it's not that it's
different, it's that it's connected
differently. That is to say, while the three
forces that are similar to each other—the
two nuclear forces and the electromagnetic forces—would be, let's say,
joining two branes,
that is, it would be the typical string that joins
two branes, the gravitational force
would actually be a string joining
itself. This would explain the big difference,
because at the
subatomic level the force of
gravity is completely irrelevant,
but at the macroscopic level—that is, of
planets, universes, what we call
galaxies—it's what defines our
universe. Okay, so it turns out
that when you do the
corresponding calculations, that is, when you use the
wave functions corresponding to the
different types of particles and so on,
this theory is correct; that is,
the numbers work out, and that there
can indeed be a type of string that is
connected to itself and that can be
completely  Different from the others, but of
course, we've already unified it. We're already
saying that the four
fundamental forces are strings, joined in
different ways. We agree, but
ultimately, strings, okay,
connections, we could say. This would be
the first problem, which is already
solved in a way on paper. Another
thing would be proving it, but on
paper it's solved. The second would be
the issue of the multiverse, what we saw about
parallel universes. Let's not say that,
well, what we talked about in the other
chapter is very abstract. Okay, a
lot of universes have been generated at a given moment. We don't
know very well how or what the
Big Man was like, but the numbers support that there is
more than one universe. When you do
the calculations, especially at the level of
quantum mechanics, what would
this theory say? Well, this theory
tells you that in reality, the different
parallel universes are defined by the
connections between the different
branes. That is, if I have three branes
and I connect one with two, well,
this would be my universe. If what I actually do
is connect one with
three, it would be a
completely different parallel universe, a third
universe.  Connecting one
to two and one to three, that is,
the sum of the two, right? So in the end,
doing the math, they've arrived at an
enormous number, that is, 10 to the power of
500, okay? Which is one of those numbers that ca
n't be pronounced, and which would be the
total number of parallel universes that would exist, that would have, let's say,
the
place where we live, which we still don't really know exactly
where it is, right? And
so this would be a bit of a point, right? That is,
as we talked about in
previous chapters, we didn't know if
the number of
parallel universes was really infinite, right? This tells you that it is
n't, that there really isn't, that it
depends on the number of branes we
consider, right? That is, what we would have to
determine is how many there really are,
right? But let's say that it already
explains it mathematically and physically, right? That is,
string theory also closes this problem, string theory, right?
And finally, what about these
five theories? Because, as I told you
at the beginning, in reality, what there have been
until very recently are five
string theories, right? Well, when
all this started to be investigated,
different physicists began to
develop different  Theories. And
unfortunately, five emerged that yielded
good results, absolutely
good, meaning there was nothing to
discuss. Obviously, one
had to be wrong because
five can't be compatible. But they
all responded correctly to mathematics and
physics.
Fortunately, it seems that for
about 20 or 25 years now, there's been
something called M-theory, which is
something like a unified
string theory. What it essentially says is that all
five theories are actually
correct at the same time, even though on paper it
might seem otherwise. How is this
possible? Well, I'm going to give you a
fairly simple example, which you
've probably seen elsewhere. Let's
say these
five theories would be the equivalent
of having the five senses that
human beings have. I mean, if we
want to perceive our reality,
we have five senses to perceive it.
Of course, if I ask you to tell me what note
this guitar is playing,
with your ear it's very simple, or
quite simple if you have trained it.
You can tell me, "This was a C."
But if I ask you to tell me
what the sound is through taste, for
example, the...  Things get complicated, they become
very, very difficult. It's like
asking me to tell you what note was
playing just by looking at it. Is it possible to
know what note was playing? Because if
I know the length of the string and I can
measure, not with my eyes, the
displacement the string has had,
I can estimate, from the frequency, what
note was playing. And
this is what happens with theories.
Theories turn out to be compatible in
pairs. That is, if you take two of them,
you can verify that they
are compatible and good, but if
you add a third, it stops working.
And you can do this with
different pairs, and it always works.
So it seems that this theory
they are unifying—the beauty of it is,
firstly, that it is very simple, and
secondly, that it seems to
actually make all five of these
theories perfectly valid and that there is no
problem between
them. Finally, to close this
episode, I would like to talk to you about something
that I consider, let's say, my
belief. If you ask me, "
What is the universe to you?", for me there is
only one answer.
I believe it's valid, and the universe
is nothing more than an extremely
complex place, but built from incredibly simple
rules.
Why do I believe this? Well, I
believe this basically because of my daily life. That is,
if we look at
nature, if we look at it from
our perspective...  What's inside our
planet, what's outside of it—if we look at
how we solve our
own problems, you realize that in the
end, the best solutions are usually
very, very, very simple.
Okay, I mean, everything that's
very complicated, everything that's very
baroque, in the end, never achieves
good solutions. That is, we always
tend to look for what's simplest, what's
most natural, or most organic. For
me, here, if we're talking about topics in
mathematics, physics, computing, and
so on, for me there are two references that
are basically clear. The first
is one that I think is a classic
when talking about these topics, which is
the Fibonacci sequence. The
Fibonacci sequence is a silly sequence, a
sequence for children, I mean, it's simply
a sequence of numbers
that anyone can carry out. It's
as simple as starting to say
numbers, starting with one, and you have to
add the last two numbers you came across.
We would start with
1, add a second value, which would be
1, and say 1 + 1, 2, 2 + 1, which is  The
previous number 3 3 + 2 5 5 + 3 8 and so on we can
go to infinity, that is, it is a
series that is so simple it is difficult
to represent mathematically.
That is, it is simple, it
has nothing, and yet when we look
at nature we find that
half of things are organized
like this, from the typical image of sunflower seeds arranged one by
one in a sunflower, in
a sunflower flower, which are arranged
in that way, the leaves when they are positioned
to receive the light are
arranged according to the Fibonacci series, the
golden ratio has to do with the
Fibonacci sequence, the
spirals we see in snails and
so on have to do with the
Fibonacci proportions, the shape of
the arms of the galaxies
has to do with the series, that is to say,
this is not by chance, that is to say, to think that this is by chance is
absurd, it makes no
sense, that is to say, we are seeing
things that are incredibly complex,
incredibly complex, that we are not
capable of understanding, and yet
their distribution would be capable of
Calculating and predicting it for a
3-year-old is practically no
mystery. It's not complicated.
The second thing is fractals.
Fractals are something that
really attracts attention. If you
haven't seen them, they might seem very
complex, but they're as
simple as using
formulas called recursive formulas. And it's
also a bit like
Fibonacci, that is, using
recursion. What is it in
Fibonacci? I'll give you an
example here. Let's say you start with a
very simple open figure, for example,
with lines. And what you do is, with
each of the lines, you replicate
the complete figure you
initially drew. Put like that, it
's a bit complicated. If you watch the video, you'll see it's not very complicated. The
funny thing is that
when you start developing
different, very simple shapes, you
realize that all trees—
the branches of the trees—are
distributed like a fractal.
Snowflakes have a fractal shape.
The veins of the leaves
have...  It's a fractal shape, meaning there are
tons of things, tons of things
that end up functioning like a fractal.
In fact, for those who want to see it
as something unsettling, Google has
a kind of engine that can
memorize images and from there
deduce what it's seeing in other
images. The neural network that it has
managed to, let's say, know if
there's a cat in a photo, as
explained in other videos, does it
through fractals, and nobody told it to
do it through fractals, okay?
That is, the neural network itself has
rearranged itself to function,
converting that image into
fractals. And from there, it's able to
deduce what it's doing. We do
n't know, but probably our
brain also has some kind of
similar system to be able to do it.
So this really catches my
attention. I mean, in the end, we're
seeing things that are very complex. I
mean, if you look at a fractal, a
fractal image, in the end it's tremendously
complex. I mean, you wouldn't be able to
draw the hand under any circumstances,
but the way you
started that drawing is for a
child, meaning it has no
mystery whatsoever.  Of course, if we
take a closer look at how
most physical laws work, from how
atoms grow, for example, based on
their molecular weight, how
we change from hydrogen to
beryllium, that is, how we increase, it's
simple. I mean, it's not like they're
rules that you learn once and
they last a lifetime because they have no
complications. However, when you take it to the
extreme, that is, when you let it
evolve for years, thousands of years,
millions of years, what you create are
incredibly complex things. It's like that
experiment,
the Game of Life. For those who haven't
seen it, there are millions of
examples on YouTube, on the internet, how from
some super silly rules of
putting squares in, and depending on
what's around them, whether they turn
dark or light,
some structures are created that seem to be
alive, they seem to move, they seem to be
shooting at each other. I
mean, these are super silly,
simple examples, and yet they lead you to
conclusions that seem very similar to
our universe. So, if you
ask me...  If I have any kind of
belief... Well, maybe
not on a religious level, but certainly on a level
about the universe, I do, and I believe that
any law or any question that is
too complicated... We haven't reached a
good conclusion, okay? I mean, the
reality is that in the end, the simplest things
are how our entire universe is composed, whether
we like it or
not, and at least that's what I think.
Greetings, and see you next week.
Bye.